"The Side Effects of Human Growth Hormone
as an Anti-Aging Therapy"
Of all the anti-aging
clinic scams,
the selling and administration
of human growth hormone
has been called
"perhaps the most blatant
and organized form
of quackery today."
It all started,
promisingly enough,
with a small trial published
in the New England
Journal of Medicine
in which 12 men
over the age of 60
who got injections
of growth hormone
gained eight pounds of lean mass
over a period of six months,
compared to nine guys
who weren't injected.
Newspapers around the world
heralded the results,
anti-aging clinics popped up
to offer the injections
for $4,700 per month or more,
and the popular press
churned out books
extolling the hormone's
age reversing properties.
After all, that's how much
muscle mass one might lose
over 10 to 20 years of aging.
That's assuming, though,
that what they gained
was muscle.
The original study
didn't measure
muscle strength or performance,
but larger, longer, and better,
i.e. placebo-controlled studies,
subsequently did,
and found zero benefit.
A meta-analysis of studies
of growth hormone
for athletic performance
found that
it may even worsen
exercise capacity.
Wait, how can you gain
pounds of lean mass,
but not get any stronger?
By retaining pounds of water.
The lean mass was mostly
just due to fluid retention.
In fact, obvious swelling,
soft tissue edema,
is one of the most common
side effects of growth hormone,
affecting about
half of recipients.
Other side effects include
joint aches,
carpal tunnel syndrome,
male breast development,
elevated blood sugars,
and new-onset diabetes.
All this with no evidence
of anti-aging effects.
If anything,
growth hormone may actually
accelerate the aging process.
For example,
those with acromegaly,
a disease
of excess growth hormone,
suffer disproportionately
from muscle weakness,
as well as diabetes,
high blood pressure,
artery dysfunction,
and bone loss.
In the 1980s,
doctors and parents
conspired to inject short kids
with growth hormone
to try to make them grow taller.
What happened to them?
A study following
thousands of children
who were injected decades ago
with growth hormone,
for one reason or another,
found they had
a 33 percent increased risk
of being dead,
largely from brain bleeds
and tumors.
The strokes would make sense
from blood pressure elevation,
and the malignancies
from the growth hormone-
induced rise
of the cancer-promoting
growth hormone IGF-1.
20,000 to 30,000 people
in the U.S.
are estimated
to use growth hormone
in a vain attempt
to combat aging,
a practice referred to in
a leading endocrinology journal
as a "medical fraud
of unprecedented proportions."
Given the adverse effects,
maybe it's good
that all the tested samples
of human growth hormone,
also known as somatotropin,
sourced from online pharmacies
were found to have
a fraction
of the labelled amount,
presumably due to degradation
from improper storage,
and the majority of samples
confiscated in another study
were counterfeit
and contained none at all.
There's also
a proliferation of pills
and nasal
or sublingual spray forms
that makes no biological sense,
as the hormone
is too large a protein
to effectively cross membranes,
and if swallowed,
is simply destroyed
in the stomach.
Given the risk of cancer
and potential
for a shortened lifespan,
one prominent clinician remarked
that maybe growth hormone
is a "true anti-aging drug"
in that it may
prematurely stop you
from growing any older.